Guide to the American Field Service Application Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Field Service application records
1917-2016
1985-1995
MS 1930
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24.34
(34 boxes)
The American Field Service Application Records comprise the history of an application filed in 1990 by American Field Service veterans of World War II for retroactive recognition as United States Army servicemen by the Pentagon under provisions of the G.I. Bill of 1977. The collection also contains research materials and publications relating to the history of the American Field Service during both world wars. The records, comprised of original documents, as well as photocopies thereof, were amassed by Joseph Porter Brinton, III, an ambulance driver with the American Field Service during World War II, who compiled the guide for their use.
Brinton, Joseph Porter
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph Porter Brinton, III, 2008 and 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Porter Brinton, III, was a member of Yale College, Class of 1945W. He received a BBA from Baruch College City University, New York, in 1957. Brinton was an ambulance driver with the American Field Service during World War II.
The American Field Service was established in 1914 as a volunteer ambulance corps. Its members, largely recruited from American colleges and universities, served in wartime Europe, primarily France.
Scope and Contents
The American Field Service Application Records comprise the history of an application filed in 1990 by American Field Service veterans of World War II for retroactive recognition as United States Army servicemen by the Pentagon under provisions of the G.I. Bill of 1977. The collection also contains research materials and publications relating to the history of the American Field Service during both world wars. The records, comprised of original documents, as well as photocopies thereof, were amassed by Joseph Porter Brinton, III, an ambulance driver with the American Field Service during World War II, who compiled a guide for their use.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in three parts and one addition: I. Main business file (original box designation B), II. Main writing file (original box designation E), and III. Boxed volume files (original box designation VB). Within these parts, the materials are arranged as received from the donor. The donor's original box designations have been preserved in the inventory of the collection, and the donor's summary of the contents of each original box (with the exception of the VB boxes) is in the first folder within the original box designations.
Ambulance drivers; Veterans -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Brinton, Joseph Porter; American Field Service
- Brinton, Joseph P. III, "Guide to the American Field Service Application Archive," typescript, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This guide explains the organization imposed by Brinton on the Main business file (B), Main writing file (E), and Boxed volume files (VB) components of the archive. Researchers wishing to use the archive should consult the guide as a preparatory step.
- Main business file (B)
  - B1, Circa 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1-91)
    This box contains earliest records of PL 95-202 applicants from 1981-1983. The first writing at the back of the box probably commenced in 1982. Content of missing papers can usually be deduced from adjacent records. The subjects include attempts to notify a disinterested and hostile AFS Corp., improper attorney report disowned by source, effort to obtain a current veterans address list, devious obstruction by Corp. Secretary R. Applewhite, test mailing to AFS veterans, report of results. No record was kept of unanswered notes to Corp. leader A. Howe. The extensive phone and in-person dealings with Applewhite were not recorded by us. The front of the box likely overlaps to a large extent with the content of B2 and perhaps B3. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B1.
  - B2, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 92-117)
    Activity from first major mailing in February 1985 until the Department of Defense suspended PL 95-202 applications in 1988 and posted new regulations in 1989. Affiliation with AFS Corp. through Howe and Applewhite and creation of the AFS Veterans Committee in final form is covered, along with problems and dealings related to writing a PL 95-202 application. B2 contains a very large amount of historical research data and notes. Written research notes are very much curtailed because the researcher (Brinton) was forced to photocopy information, maps, and photographs to save time, rather than read carefully and write notes. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B2.
  - B2, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1-72)
  - B3, Circa 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 73-105)
    Mainly 1988-1989 files relating to completion and submission of AFS application after new Department of Defense regulations for PL 95-202 were protested, but adopted. Then, the Army's Center of Miltary History produced a very sketchy, derogatory report that had to be answered. In addition, the back of the box contains a continued collection of folders devoted to individual AFS veterans leading the application or contributing to it. All formal notices and newsletters mailed between 1982 and 1991 are consolidated here. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B3.
  - B3, Circa 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1-71)
  - B4, Circa 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 72-123)
    Mainly 1989-1990 files documenting conflicts among members of the AFS Committee as judgement of the PL 95-202 application approached. At the same time, Goodwillie and Brinton facing adverse questions and demands by the Air Force board in charge at the Pentagon. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B4.
  - B4, Circa 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-13)
  - B5, Circa 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 14-147)
    Covers events from September 1990, when the founders dissolved the AFS Veterans Committee, until July 1993, when Senator Graham filed his pro-AFS entitlement bill, S. 1260, in Congress. The contents may include documentation on AFS decisions rendered by the Department of Defense PL 95-202 board, the adverse decision on the Graham-Brinton request for review in 1991, the decision entitling volunters in Burma with US 3rd CCS, the subsequent Department of Defense decision entitling AVG-Flying Tigers, and the Representative J. Tanner AFS entitlement bills submitted to Congress in 1992 and 1993. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B5.
  - B6, Circa 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1-87)
    Materials overlap B5 data on the effort to get approval from Congress, and run from late 1992 until roughly 1995. The effort to find a suitable attorney starts here with Howland in 1993. Documentation concerns many key decisions, laws, and summaries of AFS findings and claims to date. After Tom Hale reported the failure of Congress to consider supporting AFS entitlement, there was no further application activity until Cantrall filed a repeat application to the Department of Defense board in 1995. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B6.
  - B7, Circa 1995-2001 (Box 5, Folder 88-114)
    Contains application follow up activity by Brinton from roughly 1995-2001. Most of the files are organized by subject, the most recent being Bissler's effort to employ military attorney E. Fidell in Washington. Also included are materials on George Bush. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B7.
  - B7, Circa 1995-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1-101)
  - B8, Circa 1986-1996 (Box 6, Folder 102-111)
    Contains information about the work of Associate Editor William R. Cantrall, including research and advice that he provided during the period 1986-1990, and Brinton's assistance in Cantrall's ill-advised and ill-fated repeat PL 95-202 application to the Department of Defense board during 1994-1996. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B8.
  - B8, Circa 1986-1996 (Box 7, Folder 1-52)
  - B9, Circa 1985-1993 (Box 7, Folder 53-82)
    Contains documentation regarding three different elements of AFS Committee application business: financial records; response sheets from AFS veterans; and address lists and other information regarding AFS veterans. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of B9.
  - B9, Circa 1985-1993 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
- Main writing file (E)
  - E1, Circa 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 9-25)
    Contains outlines and drafts for the eventual AFS Application book copyright, circa 1988-1989. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of E1.
  - E2, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 8, Folder 26-34)
    Contains the first draft of the AFS Application text, and possibly some supporting research material. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of E2.
  - E2, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
  - E3, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 9, Folder 9-56)
    Contains research materials gathered for the AFS Application, but for the most part not used. Includes documents, illustrations, and maps. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of E3.
  - E4, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 10, Folder 1-65)
    Contains partially organized research data used to compile the AFS Application book. Includes photocopies of overseas records regarding AFS veterans from the nascent, poorly organized AFS archive in New York City, and affidavits of AFS veterans illustrating service rendered to the U.S. Army overseas. Includes documents, illustrations, and maps. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of E4.
  - E5, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 10, Folder 66-85)
    Contains various versions of the extremely important summaries that the AFS PL 95-202 applicants composed and distributed to describe their wartime service. The information above was excerpted from notes supplied by the donor, which are in the first folder of E5.
  - E5, Circa 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1-22)
- Boxed volume files (VB), Circa 1917-1989
  Contains various copies and files relating to the AFS Application, including a World War I-era photograph of AFS ambulances in the field. The donor did not provide notes or summaries about the content of the original VB boxes. According to information supplied by the donor, box VB3 was donated to Princeton University Library, box VB4 to the Harvard University, Widener Library, and box VB5 to Harvard University Archives, Pusey Library. Box VB6 was distributed to libraries noted above. Box VB2 contained an exact duplicate copy of the contents of Box VB1 and was discarded.
  - VB1 (Box 11, Folder 23-24)
  - VB1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - VB7-VB8 (Box 12, Folder 2-24)
- Books and other published research materials relating to the American Field Service
  - German World War II propaganda, Circa 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Printed ephemera aimed at demoralizing Allied soldiers.
  - Rock, George. The History of the American Field Service, 1920-1955. New York: Platen Press, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Desloge, Joseph, Jr. Passport to Manhood: Adventures of a WW II Front Line Ambulance Driver with the British and the French Foreign Legion, self-published book, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Desert Rat Sketch Book, related materials, Circa 1959 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Saber, Clifford. Desert Rat Sketch Book. Franklin Square, New York: Sketchbook Press, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Saber, Clifford. Six Color Prints from Desert Rat Sketch Book. Franklin Square, New York: Sketchbook Press, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Gleason, Arthur. Our Part in the Great War. New York: Frederick A. Stokes, 1917 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Gilmore, Scott. A Connecticut Yankee in the 8th Gurkha Rifles. London: Brassey's, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Seymour, James W. D. Memorial Volume of the American Field Service in France, 1914-1917. Boston: American Field Service, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Inventory of publications donated to Yale in 2008 and to be donated later by Joseph Brinton III, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Britain against Germany, 1939-1945. British Information Services pamphlet, 1945 December (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Victory in Burma. British Information Services pamphlet, 1945 July (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Lapsley, James Thomas III. Gentleman Volunteers: American Ambulance Drivers in the First World War. M.A. thesis (History): University of California, Santa Cruz, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Gilbo, Patrick F. The American Red Cross. New York: Harper and Row, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Publications on the American Field Service, 1942-1995 (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
  - Axel Jansen correspondence relating to American Field Service history, Circa 1995 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Additional material, 1937-2016; Accession 2018-m-0043
  - Publications
    - Application for Entitlement of American Field Service Military Personnel to U.S. Army Discharges and Veterans Administrative Benefits
      - American Field Service Application, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      - American Field Service Application, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
      - American Field Service Application, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - American Field Service Application copy 15, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
      - American Field Service Application copy 15, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
      - American Field Service Application Guide to Application Archive, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - American Field Service Application Guide for Attorney Sec. 401, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - American Field Service Application India pages, deleted from chapter 11, pages 2-38, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - American Field Service Application, On Active Duty with the US Army, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - American Field Service Application parts one and two, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - American Field Service Application parts one and two, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
      - American Field Service Application parts one and two, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
      - American Field Service Application, Roster of American Field Service Volunteers of WWI and WWII Eligible for US Army Discharge, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - American Field Service Application summary, Brinton copy, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - American Field Service Application, World War One, Conformity to New Regulations, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - American Field Service Application, World War One and Two, house copy, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - American Field Service Application, World War One and Two, house copy, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - American Field Service Application, World War One and Two, Request for Review, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - American Field Service Application Volume 2-A, two versions of explanation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - American Field Services Application Supplement
      - Application Supplement, 1977-2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Application Supplement, 2006-2011 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
      - Final extras, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - First draft pages, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Removed pages, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Newsletters and magazines
      Arrangement
      The accession is arranged into three groupings: publications, subject files and correspondence, and personal files.
      The accession consists of the American Field Service Application, filed in 1990 by American Field Service veterans of World War II for retroactive recognition as United States Army servicemen by the Pentagon under provisions of the G.I. Bill of 1977. The accession includes multiple copies and drafts of the application, as well as correspondence, research files, and personal files of Joseph P. Brinton III, who was heavily involved in the formation of the application.
      - American Field Service drivers list, 1937-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      - American Field Service general publications, Circa 1960s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 3-5)
      - American Field Service general publications, 1990-2015 (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
      - American Field Service general publications, 1996-2015 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
      - American Field Service Letters (formally News Bulletin), 1942-1945 (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
      - American Field Service Letters (formally News Bulletin), 1942-1945 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - American Field Service Roll of Honor, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - New Crusader, Journal of the Eighth Army Veterans Association, 1988-2002 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
      - World War Two Tributes to American Field Service, 50th Anniversary Driver's Reunion, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Subject files and correspondence
    - Archives guide, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Special American Field Service excerpts, 1946-1976 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Extract Edition part 2, 1949-1950 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript for Appeal, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Original manuscript of response to U.S. historian's unsatisfactory report, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - World War One response, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1st draft, new information, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript pages for much used eight page summary, 1990-2003 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - American Field Service 1st drafts, archive guide, Circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Guide to American Field Service Application, manuscript data worksheets, Circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Extra file box sheets, 1981-2003 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Extra Pics Prints, Circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Office of Strategic Services, 1988-1993 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Thank You correspondence, 1955-2002 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Charles Loizeaux entitlement case, 1997-1999 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Boaz, Ralph Evans, Purple Heart application case, 1991-1994 (Box 13, Folder 16-22)
    - Long, Malcolm Elliott, and Richard W. Nelson, 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - World War Two bibliography, Circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Angell, Jim, and Jim Sutton, 1986-1990 (Box 13, Folder 25-26)
    - Extract of American Field Service Veterans Committee Report of Historian, 1981-1990 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Special sheets research, 1982-1992 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous reference data, 2007 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - American Field Service Youth and western trip itinerary, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Application books, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Print supplement expense, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - American Field Service donation expense, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - American Field Service correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - American Field Service archives, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Golobic, Eleanora, 1991-2005 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Welles, Edward O., 2001 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - ISBN library classification article, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Yale Alumni, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Howard, Michael, Yale file, 1989-1991 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Yale press releases, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Camurat, Diane, author, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, Joseph Brinton's room, 1988-2005 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Cantrall, William R., 2011 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Nelson, Richard, extras, 2008-2010 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - American Field Service duplicates, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Squire, Chick, 2009 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - American Field Service group photo, Circa 1940s (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - American Field Service clippings, 2009-2010 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Extract of Cumings Origins of the Korean War, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - American Field Service miscellaneous material, 2008 (Box 14, Folder 21-23)
    - Bombed in Casalbordino, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Chamberlin, Ward, The War, 2007 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Edward, Joyce, 2006-2008 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Albright, Alan, 1990-2010 (Box 14, Folder 27-32)
    - Newsclippings, 2005-2007 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Discoveries, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Barres, Oliver M., 2003 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Nierenberg, Judith, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Sanders, Sol, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Yonts, Charles, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Calendar, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Late page extra and late news, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Book part one, World War Two response to Historian, new pages not inserted, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - Extras, Xerox pages, Circa 1989 (Box 14, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous drafts, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 43)
    - Postscripts, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - American Field Service research papers, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Newsletter sheets, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - American Field Service committee termination, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - American Field Service newsletters, Circa 1950s-1970s (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Volunteer drivers, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - American Field Service clippings, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Bowen, John G., records, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - American Field Service news, 1947-1948 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Army maps, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - World War Two diary notes, Circa 1940s (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Italy Clippings, World War Two, Sorrento, Circa 1960s (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Italy maps and notes, Circa 1950s (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
    - Miami Herald Treasure Coast, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Veteran Affairs, 2016 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - World War Two news, Circa 1990s (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Addresses, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Kimball, Paul, reference list, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Brinton, Joseph files and writing, Circa 1940s-1980s (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Brinton, Joseph, correspondence, 2012-2016 (Box 15, Folder 20-21)
    - Six Color Prints From Desert Rat Sketch Book, Sketchbook Press, Franklin, New York, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Personal files
    - Photographs
      - Allemang, Richard, Circa 1940s (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - American Field Service Application archive, photographs and negatives, Circa 1988 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - American Field Service general, 1944-1985 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - American Field Service office, Circa 1961 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Brinton, Joseph P., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Craig, Charles W., 2005 gifted photographs, Circa 1940s (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Italy, 1940-1949 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Italy negatives, Circa 1940s (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Ponselet, Vivian, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - World War One, US Army ambulance, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - World War Two, 1942-1988 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - World War Two, Dodge T-211 ambulance, Circa 1990s (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook
      - American Field Service scrapbook compiled by Joseph P. Brinton, 1946 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Scrapbook of photographs taken in Italy, compiled by Joseph P. Brinton, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 1)